Guide to the Robert Hofstadter Papers SC0426
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2011-187
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, X-Ray Astronomy, 1965-1986 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence, Synchrotron Noninvasive Angiography, Development, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Correspondence, Harshaw Chemical Co., 1972-1986 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence, Congratulations, Nobel Prize, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, Congratulations, National Medal of Science, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Correspondence, Nobel Prize Ceremonies, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Correspondence, Mainz Honorary Degree, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence, Wolf Prize Nominations, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence, Congratulations, Election to National Academy of Sciences, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence, Bologna Honorary Degree, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence, Padova University Honorary Degree, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence, Harvey Prize Nominations, 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence, California Scientist of the Year, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Lecture Notes and Teaching Materials
    Materials related to courses taught by Hofstadter in the Stanford University Department of Physics.
    - Physics 21, Lecture Demonstration Illustrations, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Student Evaluations, Physics 11, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Photographs
    Photographs of Hofstadter; his family; colleagues; professional events; and research equipment and facilities.
    - Research, devices, construction, facilities, 1945-1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Portraits, informal, family, circa 1945-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Portraits, informal, events, colleagues, family, circa 1945-1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Personnel picture books, Hansen Labs and SLAC, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Photographs of colleagues and mementos of family, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Meeting of Korean Physical Society, 1972 Sep 7-9 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Publications and Writings
    - Book Reviews, circa 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Research
    Includes drafts, notes, lab notebooks, raw data, graphical representations of findings, reports, proposals, and related documents. Also included are materials collected by or sent to Hofstadter due to their relation to his research, as well as related correspondence.
    - Notebook: Abroad, Italy, circa 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Norden Labs, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Presentations
    - Congressional Testimony, 1973-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Retirement Talk, Notes, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Big Science and Little Science," St. Catherine's, Cumberland Lodge, 1966 June (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Travel and Conferences
    - Australia Trip, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - China Trip, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Haverford College Visit, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Japan Trip, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re: Marie Sklodowska-Curie, Travel to Warsaw, Poland, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Second International Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy Conference, 1958 Sep (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Nuclear Sizes Conference, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Oversized Items
  This series is comprised of oversize items separated during processing.
  - Mapped calculations, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Atomic Nucleus," illustration, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Compton Scattering Process, mapped calculations and graphs, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asian tour poster, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Symposium Celebrating 35 Years of Electron Scattering and Nuclear Particle Science, poster, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Honorary Degree, Carleton University, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NASA Certificate of Appreciation, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brandeis University Associate Honors certificate, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Honorary Degree, Seoul National University, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Research lab, oversize photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Electromagnets, U.S. Information Agency press release, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 350th Anniversary of Galileo’s "Dialoghi Sui Due Massimi Sistemi Del Mondo," Symposium, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NASA Flight Badge award for successful launch of Compton Gamma Ray Observatory (given posthumously), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Technical drawings from research on high-energy particle detectors (Hansen Labs, 1000 Mev), circa 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cavendish Experiment, figures and data on strength of gravity, circa 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Electron Electron Scattering - Original," calculations of results, circa 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Electron Deuteron Scattering - Original," calculations of results, circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Outgoing Electron Scattering - Original," calculation of results, circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Deuteron Book," calculation of results, circa 1931 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Change Densities," calculations of results, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Rosenbluth Scattering," results and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Form Factors," calculations of results, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Patent Application, "Means for Detecting Ionizing Radiations", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scientific Products Co., calendar featuring Hofstadter for October-December, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Double Focusing Spectrometer Design Data, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Oversize clippings, circa 1950-1990 (Box 4)
  - Portrait photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Portrait photograph, proof, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lawrence Labs staff photograph, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Microwave Lab staff photograph, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hansen Labs staff photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Physics Department staff photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - San Francisco Examiner photographs to accompany interview, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Portrait photograph at KMS Fusion, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Instituts Internatinaux de Physique et de Chime, Brussels, photograph of meeting participants, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Felix Bloch Symposium, posters, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stanford Physics meetings, framed photographs (2), undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - American Academy of Achievement, Golden Plate Award, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Rontgen Symposium poster, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Universite Libre de Bruxelles, lecture on calcium isotopes, poster, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - American Physical Society Meeting, oversize photograph of attendees, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lunar landscape photographs, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Symposium sign, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - American Physical Society Meetings and Association of Physics Teachers, photograph of luncheon participants, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Magnetic Spectrometer Gauges, technical drawing, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2014-073
  - Conference of Nobel Laureates, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conference of Nobel Laureates, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conference of Nobel Laureates, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - W. W. Hansen Laboratories - Personnel Picture Book, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nobel Ceremony program, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nobel Ceremony, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Princeton Atomic Physics Course 308, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Weizmann, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Medal of Science, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Nice Letters" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - RH Correspondence with Stanford Colleagues, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Patents (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Max H. Stein Professorship (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Norden Work/Summary, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Princeton Optics Course Physics 202, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter by RH re scientists' responsibility, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Neutron research clipping, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Trip to Europe, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Max Shiffman (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Salary Letters (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tributes/Honors (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letter - John Wheeler to RH re move to Stanford, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jewish Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Installation of mass spectrometer in HEPL end station (slides) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - National Academy of Sciences photographs, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Congressional testimony re laser fusion photographs (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brazil photographs, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General Motors Research Labs speech, 1961 Nov (Box 1)
  - High-Energy Electron Scattering Tables, by Robert Herman and Robert Hofstadter (2 copies), 1960 (Box 1)
  - Oversize photographs, including Nobel Ceremony (Box 2)
  - Early sodium-iodide crystals (discovered to be a very powerful scintillator by RH), 1948 (Box 3)
  - Talk at INS Symposium on Particle Physics, Tokyo, Japan, 1979; 3.1; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Laser Fusion Talk, 3.2; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Talk I gave on Laser Fusion at GM research, 1975 Seo 23; 3.3; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Talk at [L?] on crystal ball, 1982 Jun 28; 3.4; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Schiff Lecture, 1986; 3.5; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Colloquium "Synchrotron Radiation and Coronary Angiography" (Los Alamos), 1983 Jul 12; 3.6; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - "The Gamma Ray Observatory" Near Zero Conference, 1982 Mar; 3.7; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - [Lindau?], 1985; 3.7; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2018-014
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_01; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_02; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_03; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_04; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_05; 1 videotape(s) (beta) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_06; 1 videotape(s) (beta) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_07; 1 videotape(s) (beta) (Box 1)
  - Robert Hofstadter Retirement Symposium/Celebration, circa 1984-1985; 1_08; 1 videotape(s) (beta) (Box 1)